Hello and welcome back to
another episode with, ItsDrDan.
Today we're going to be learning
how to convert D and L glucose from
a fissure to a Haworth projection.
Now, what makes this so different than my
previous videos on the Haworth projections
is that D and L are enantiomers of
one another, meaning that the Haworth
projection is going to end up being
flipped because of that enantiomer shape.
So we're going to go through this
step by step and show exactly
how to do this for glucose.
First thing that we're going to
do is have our Fischer projection
and I have the OHs here labeled in
red so you can see the difference
and make it a little bit easier.
So we're going to first start
by drawing the enantiomer.
Now when we go through this and draw
that enantiomer, remember that entire
thing, the way to look at that is This
is a mirror image or reflection, right?
So it's just like yourself.
You're looking in the mirror
and you're waving at yourself.
So the first thing that I would do is
I would redraw that general backbone
just like how we have before and the
things that are going to be mirrored
that are the important parts are the OH's
because they are on those chiral carbons.
Right?
So we have a chiral carbon
here, here, here, and here.
Those are all shown by
those different crosses.
So when we are writing that we
are going to fill in, I always
like to start with the OHs.
So that way you're, you're just
going to fill in the important
functional group and each one of
these is paired with a hydrogen.
So there's a hydrogen on one side.
Oh, H on the other.
So I'll write down maybe like one
side, so like on the left I have
OH, H, OH, OH, and then I'll write
all the pairs on the right side.
Just like so.
So we have our enantiomer.
Now, what exactly does that mean?
So that means on the right side I now
have L glucose for the other structure.
How can you tell if it's L or D?
Well, the way to remember if it's L or
D has to do with the last chiral carbon.
So if we kind of go through
these, right, each one of these
here, like I said, are chiral.
And what we're going to do is we're
going to look at the last one in the
line, so the one I put a little red
star next to, this is the last one.
And what we can see is, well, on the,
on the left structure, the OH is on the
right side, so for D, um, so for dexter.
So D is on, on the right, and
that is going to be our right RD.
Now on the bottom one,
we have L is on the left.
So L here, we will denote that with
the letter L to say that this is left.
So D and L.
Now let's go on to our next step.
All right.
So our next step is all about
rotating the Fisher projection.
So for this, I already went
through the process of rotating it.
What we will do is we're
going to rotate it 90 degrees.
to the right.
Now the reason why we are doing this is
so that it helps us see a couple things.
The first one is we want to make sure
that we keep all of our carbons numbered.
It's really important to see where
all your OHs are going to be going
because it matters if they're top
or bottom on your final structure.
So we have 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, so we
have all those individual numbers.
Now, what is also important about
top and bottom here is what I mean
is, notice how we have some OHs
on the bottom of our structure.
So if we kind of imagine a little,
a little border line that we have
here, we have some that are on the
bottom, some that are on the top.
So what we'll do is we will label that.
So this is going to be top.
And in green we are going to have bottom.
And it's going to be the same idea too
for the other structure or the enantiomer.
So for D and L we will keep our same idea.
We'll number it as well 1, 2, 3, And we
will also have our top and bottom for L.
And you can see already that both
of these are flipped as a result
of R being a different isomer.
So all the OHs for the L one are
all going to be pointing, most of
them are going to be pointing up.
Or as you can see for D, most
of them are pointing down.
So it's going to be a really
big difference in our structure.
Let's look at the next step.
For step 3, what makes this so different
is that we need to be able to figure
out how big is our ring going to be.
Most monosaccharides, or simple sugars,
are generally a 5 or a 6 member ring.
meaning it's going to be one of these
two shapes that I have written down here.
Now, the one thing that's different
about the numbering here is
notice that I have a number on
our ox, on an oxygen on the ring.
These are both considered
to be heterocyclic rings.
Okay.
Being that hetero meaning different.
So what makes it heterocyclic is that it
has a, uh, oxygen embedded in the ring.
So whenever we have a
heterocyclic species, that means
we have something different.
So when we are going through these,
we're going to have to number them.
Before I had it just by
numbering the carbons, right?
We went, we started the carbonyl.
We numbered all the way down.
We're gonna do the same idea, but this is
what I always call an unofficial numbering
because alls we wanna know is how big
our ring is when we go through this.
So once again, we're gonna
start at the C double bond O.
So always at the carbon yield
is your first number, regardless
of if it's an Aldo or a keto.
We are going to start at this
one for just how big is the ring?
So we have 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, and then we're
going to that last chiral carbon, so
we're gonna put a little red star next to
it again, and our last numbered spot is
going to be the oxygen that is on the last
alcohol, alright, so that's gonna be 6.
meaning that this structure is
going to have the same shape
as the one on the top left.
So we will have our six member ring,
just like so, and it's going to have
an OH on the structure, and it's
going to look something like this.
And we can redraw the numbering on here.
It's going to be one, two, three.
4, 5, 6.
And that 6 oxygen that's here on this
ring comes from this chiral spot.
And if you came here to figure
out mechanisms, go to my
hemiacetal and acetal video.
I will go through the
mechanism of how to do this.
This is more how to draw
Haworth projections quickly.
So now it's the same idea
for this other structure.
It's going to be the same thing.
Being that they're both enantiomers, their
skeletal structure It's still the same.
It's the chirality is the different part.
So we're only putting the ring here.
It's only the carbons
that we're interested in.
So both of these structures are
going to be that six member ring.
So let's go on to our next step here.
Step four is all about where
to place all of your OH groups.
So previously I mentioned that it's
very important that we go through
and number our rings because we need
to make sure that we are placing
everything in the right spot.
So let's first start with the OH groups.
So if we notice we have this general
shape, so we have our hemiacetal
structure, we have our anomeric carbon
that is on number one, so we'll talk
about the anomeric carbon in a little bit.
That's just, we're just going to
place that facing up in the meantime.
So, now, for our next groups, we're
going to put in red all of our OH groups.
So we're going to go
from carbon to carbon.
So carbon one was the aldehyde
that turned into an alcohol.
Now carbon two, the OH
is pointing down, right?
So being that we see that downward, we're
going to fill that in going down as well.
We're now going to move to carbon three.
Carbon three, we see that
it is on the top side.
So being that this is top, We
are going to go through and
we're going to put it going up.
Now carbon 4, we see that
it is going down, so we're
going to fill that in as well.
Now carbon 5 is different
than all the others.
Now why is that?
Well, if you remember
from your reactions here.
This particular carbon this one
is where this OH is what's doing
the bonding So that OH there let's
color code that for ourselves.
So this OH let's make it we'll
make it Um, how about green?
So being that we have our green O
that one is what is going to become
a part of the ring structure itself
So something happens here when this
chain Opened or right before it closed,
it goes to a process known as Muta
rotation, which can cause this last
TH two group here that's on carbon
number six to rotate either up or down.
Now, how do you know where it's gonna go?
Because we have six carbons.
So on Carbon five.
We have a c H two oh group that's going to
be pointing either up or down, and it has
to do with whether or not it was D or L.
So if it was D, it's
going to be pointing up.
If it was L, it's gonna be pointing down.
We're gonna put that in, so we have
a c H two, and it's going to be
pointing up, and we can see that here.
Now what's the difference between
what we were doing before?
Well, if we go to the
other structure for L.
So that's down here.
How are they going to compare?
Well, L, where we're going, once again,
we're going to go through the entire
process of filling everything in.
So if we start at carbon number one, So
let's go through and renumber everything.
So we got 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, and
then we have 1, 2, 3, 4, 5.
And then carbon number six.
We're numbering our carbons this time.
'cause we already know our ring size.
So official numbering.
So the first thing is, where
does the CH two oh H go?
Let's go.
Let's start with that one.
Like how we did last time while being
that it is L, it's this time it's
gonna be pointing down as a result.
So what we're going to do is in our
structure, We are going to have a
CH2OH inside, like so, pointing down,
and we are going to write it like so.
And here, let's make this ink size
a little bit smaller, so that way
we can see it a little better.
So CH2OH, alright?
So that's pointing down
on carbon number five.
Now for the other carbons, what
is going to be so different is
we're going to do the same thing.
We're going to go through this, and
we're going to put our OHs pointing
up and down, going carbon to carbon.
So carbon 2, we have up.
Carbon 3 is down.
Carbon 4 is up.
So up, down, up.
It's like kind of having
a cheat code in a game.
So we have up, down, and then up.
And that is what our
structure would look like.
Now comparing the two, so if I
bring the other one down, We can
see that the OH groups are flipped
between the different structures.
Notice how the top one is, uh, if
we go through here, we see down,
up, down between 2, 3, and 4.
And on the other structure,
it's up, down, up.
So this is the difference between
whenever we have a D structure and
an L structure for these two pieces.
Let's go on to the last little
bit about alpha and beta anomers.
Step five in the final step is all
about alpha and beta anomers, which
tends to be one of the most confusing
parts for going over carbohydrates.
Now why is that?
Well mainly it's because both
alpha and beta can exist.
Now what is an alpha or a beta?
Well it's all about looking
at the anomeric carbon.
So, for all of these, the anomeric carbon
is wherever we have a hemiacetal, meaning
that we are looking for an ether and
an alcohol connected to the same spot.
Or, on a disaccharide, this could
be also the acetal or the ketal.
So, on this structure, the one
thing that we are seeing is, it's
all about where are the CH2 and
the CH2OH, where are they facing?
So we are always looking at two areas.
So if I have, right down below, I
have both D glucose and L glucose.
In order to tell if something
is beta, so beta is all about,
beta is cis, alpha is trans.
So what exactly are we referring to
with cis and trans, because usually
people think about double bonds.
So for something to be cis, the
CH2OH and your anomeric OH must
either both be pointing up, like a,
like a touchdown or a field goal, or
they must be both be pointing down.
Now, on Trans, well, you might be
able to guess it, well, if they're
both pointing down or up together
for beta, or cis, they're the same.
On trans, it's all about, well, if one
of them is pointing, let's say, up, the
other one is going to be pointing down.
Okay, so think of these
kind of like little arrows.
pointing up, pointing down.
Now in order for something to be
the opposite, right, for the other
side, it's the same general thing.
If one's pointing up, the
other one must be pointing down
for CH2OH on the other side.
So if we were to kind of look at
all those structures above, we
can further classify each of these
individual, uh, rings here that we have.
Now, if we look at the first one on
the left hand side, what do you see?
Well, the CH2OH is pointing up and
the OH itself is also pointing up.
And in fact, we can even draw this so
that way, It is pointing up so that way
it helps illustrate an up for you, right?
Because that is the correct way.
So being that is the case, this
is technically beta D glucose
because of that rotation.
Now for this other one, you can see that,
oh, well we have an OH that's pointing
And we have our, our, our CH2OH on the
inside of the ring is pointing down.
So this is referred to as alpha L glucose.
How do you know if it's alpha or beta?
How do you know where this OH went?
Because I just put it going up.
It can also be going down as well.
The reason is, going back up here,
is the ring is able to reopen itself.
It can open and close.
Now when this happens, the OH could
rotate where it's either pointing up
or it's pointing down as a result.
In fact, with most carbohydrates in
the body, 63 percent of them exist
as beta, the other 37 act as alpha.
So now, how do you know
with your problems?
Most of the time it's generally
specified in homework and exam
problems which one to draw.
And if not, they might
ask you to draw both.
So for this problem, you can see
that we did alpha and beta here.
So if, let's say if we just copy and paste
this here, how would you draw the other?
Well, it's all about
just flipping that OH.
So if we erase here and here, so in
order to do the other, it would just be
all about, well, before we had beta D.
So if we make alpha D, we can
see, oh, hey, the OH is down.
So that's alpha D and then beta
L, you would have them both being
pointing in the same direction.
So now they're both pointing as
a result and we can just flip the
OH and that's all you have to do.
They both exist naturally in your body
and they both get metabolized different
ways because of alpha or beta or L or D.
They all have different purposes for
what they're going to be used for.
That's this video on how to do
Hayworth Projections for both L and D.
I hope this helped you.
Please keep, hit that like and
subscribe button if it did and comment
below, let me know what you thought.
All the comments, I love answering them
and I love hearing back from you guys.
Alright, thank you so much and
I hope you have a wonderful
day and I'll see you all later.
Bye now.